well
I have sat down
I mean I just recorded 30 minutes of
rambling
and realized I've said nothing
so I've re-recorded
this is uh I've done this I've done this
take a few times not even just today
I've actually sat down to record this
a lot of times
and I try to do this without notes
because I think that notes
I really want to say what needs to be
said you know
and sometimes my thoughts can be
organized by writing and sometimes they
can be
um overly
analytically
um hard to follow
like a wordy you know
and I want to be I want to talk to you I
want to I want you to listen to me you
know I don't want you to feel like I'm
reading a some sort of psychology book
to you I don't want you to feel like I'm
you know reading off my bullet points
or
um
I'm going to get that it's a one-sided
conversation
but I hope that you're listening
you know I I don't want you to tune out
I don't want you to
this is the one of the biggest things
that
that I seem to come across when it comes
to men's mental health is and people
don't listen I mean really
any mental health it's one of those
things everybody thinks that anxiety and
depression and mental health is a break
glass in case of emergency situation
and it's seriously not that we
we feel good we feel all right we're not
thinking about that thing we're busy
so we don't think about it we don't
bring it up we're feeling all right cool
and then it comes up later and it
catches us off guard and that's when we
desperately we reach out to friends like
me and say dude I'm [ __ ] I'm like help
my brain's not working right right now
and I'll tell you everything I can and I
send you a bunch of links and I send you
a bunch of videos and I send you a bunch
of Articles and I tell you to read this
book and I tell you I send you this
video and I send you a podcast I did and
I all these things
um
you know and you don't [ __ ] listen
you don't listen because you're waiting
till it's time for an emergency to solve
these very real problems that you're
walking around with every single day all
day they don't go away
you're just not thinking about they're
not the Forefront of your mind because
there's other things that need to be
taken care of
but below the surface these things that
are causing you turmoil are Brewing
they're chilling dude
they're they're there so
you know
I don't want to say this as you know if
any of my like friends like close
friends or people who have reached out
to me you know through the spot because
I've had a lot of people reach out to me
personally
um you know and ask for advice and ask
for help and stuff and it's the same
instance of they ask for help when their
house is on fire and it's like what do
you want me to do man
like you want me to throw water balloons
at your burning house you have to
[ __ ] deal with this stuff when you're
not suffering and I know that that sucks
to hear and that really sucks to hear
because
like who's got the time you know this
seems like some sort of hobby right this
seems like some sort of like oh well
that's the thing that that guy's
interested in
that guy likes mental health stuff
that's a fun hobby of his
like nah dog I was gonna murder myself
when I was 26 I was gonna I had a gun
against my temple I just knew that I was
part of the 27 Club the 27 Club is uh
artists and creatives and musicians
they when they're 27 years old they
overdose or they kill themselves or they
they're just some sort of thing
and I had that I didn't tell anybody but
it was just weird background task
there's just this thing that I knew and
accepted and like it in my head me to me
yeah I'm gonna die when I'm 27 I'm an
artist I'm a real artist like what
listen to that Madness what the hell
that was just a background task that I
didn't deal with that I didn't
sit with you know
so
you know I guess I say that
hopefully from a place of vulnerability
and not a place of um
you know if like if you have never put a
gun against your temple like don't think
that uh well I'm doing all right then I
haven't got that far yet like no man if
you're here if you're listening to this
if you're suffering you don't need
other people's story to validate it man
you're suffering
your suffering stuff sucks you're
feeling depression you're feeling
anxiety you're feeling the feelings of
depression you're feeling the human
feelings of anxiousness and our modern
world what it does we label everything
we identify everything it's like the way
that our we think like in the Western
World our structures of thought actually
label everything
we identify with everything and so when
you have you know a few weeks a few
months a few years
maybe a decade whatever you got going on
if you have this consistent time of like
every day every other day a few times a
week whatever it is of
feeling depression after a while it's
like of course you're going to start to
say yeah I'm depressed I mean I feel
depressed
like you identify with you label with it
and you know and I don't say that as
it's like a bad thing you know you know
listen listen carefully here you know
I'm not
we label ourselves as things so we can
we have this part of our mind you know
the ego part of our mind really
it likes knowing it likes feeling safe
where it's at it likes knowing that
it knows who itself is
so when it could say like I'm a
depressed person suddenly it knows like
cool here's where I sit here's what like
cool I'll feel safe it's like we almost
we trick ourselves into labeling
labeling ourselves as I'm a depressed
person I have depression like it's like
some sort of you know like growth on our
neck like yeah I've got it you know and
there is some senses of thinking about
that because I think depression and
anxiety is you know if you've never
heard of this example before you know if
you have uh if you break your leg and
your legs in a cast you know it's very
visible you can see like wow this dude's
got a broken leg and it's it's in pain
does not work properly it has to it has
to heal it has to sit there it has to
just wait and not be put on under a
bunch of strain and there's not a bunch
of like when you have a broken leg you
don't all right what you need is Sprints
man you need Sprints every day for a
month straight and that thing will get
so strong and sturdy you won't even have
to face the truth that it's broken bone
nah you gotta relax you gotta just chill
out you gotta let the body do what it
does and your mind is kind of the same
way
you have to
you know we we see the broken leg but we
don't see the depression we don't we
maybe we'll see the anxiety maybe we'll
see the sadness maybe we'll see kind of
the hunched over shoulders you know we
see it in ourselves we'll see in other
people like you know what it looks like
when someone's depressed you know you
picture you know someone with a hood up
you know and if they're happy if they're
not depressed if they're confident if
they're um you know fulfilled within
their own life their chest is out their
shoulders are back you know they're
they're
um their posture is taller their spine
is erect you know there's a difference
you know we we don't necessarily see
depression like we would see you know
very visibly broken leg for example but
you know there is
um telltale signs you know we could see
within ourselves
um but the the reason why I say that is
is
the
the structures in which we think in our
Western World and when I say Western you
know
the US you know
the Western World we think differently
than the rest of the world if you didn't
know if you haven't watched the damn
video If you haven't you know listen to
other people outside of your hometown we
think differently our structure of what
we learn the knowledge that we gain the
books we read the way we're taught the
the
um delicacy in which we're taught the
aggressiveness of which we're taught the
everything
that
we are this whole structure has built
upon it you know we think we are these
people this person who is like if I was
just born
into you know a village of 150 people
and I never had a phone I never had
technology I never had
um you know all these experiences we
think would probably pretty much be the
same person just you know with less
stuff but we we would be so
unrecognizable to ourselves you know the
structure you're not just born this
thing and you're exactly who you are
because you were born that way that's a
lot of this problem here a lot of us
think we're like oh I'm born with
depression no no
there's genetic markers there's
um you know epigenetic expression
experiences and traumas and these things
that can you know depression and these
sorts of things and mental health issues
do run in my family but that doesn't
mean that
my experience is out here
correlate and and and
let me back up
see this is more of what I keep doing
with these every time I sit down to
record this I kind of feel like I get
into these Corners where I I I recognize
that I'm not speaking as clearly as I
should like I like I recognize the
people who are listening right now may
be like okay what are you what are you
saying what are you talking about and
that's
that's kind of how this stuff goes man
this is this is philosophical you're
contemplating your mind there's nothing
to do right now but listen and allow the
words to like move through your body and
Usher in Epiphany I always like to say
that ushering in of epiphany we think
we're the ones who solve everything we
think we're the ones like all right cool
if I read these books then I me
personally will know exactly what to do
and it's like sometimes when you're
reading the books the information is is
being Unwound underneath you inside of
you the
um false beliefs of who you think
yourself to be or what you thought
before you read that book if you're
willing and you're open to it and that
piece of information that you're
consuming it can change who you are at
the level and you don't the thing is
you don't go I am going to consciously
choose to change who I am now now that I
have read this important piece of
information you know it doesn't work
like that we know it doesn't work like
that you have to allow these things kind
of work underneath the surface and what
happens back to what I was saying with
us not listening we get in the [ __ ]
way because we think we know we
seriously think we know the answers like
guys I'm talking right see I'm looking
you right in the damn eye you don't
[ __ ] know if you knew you wouldn't be
in this position you need more
information you need more knowledge you
need to learn you need to step outside
of your ego you need to step outside of
the way that you've been doing things
and you need to try something different
if the way that you've been doing things
is not working out for you try something
different
you know I think a lot of this
depression stuff when we identify with
it it allows us to not take
responsibility for it and this sucks and
this feels very uncomfortable to hear
and if you're hearing it like please
just keep listening
take responsibility for the way you're
feeling
do not blame it on genetics on the story
The societies like
we're depressed and we're a depressed
society and suddenly like oh I guess I'm
depressed too and you know like that's
don't let them do that to you bro that
takes away your power
I did that for so many years I like I
was someone who is depressed I'm a
depressed person I went to the doctors
and you have a a three minute four
minute conversation with these people
and they're right on your chart cool yep
you have bipolar depression they run on
a truck cool you have major depression
disorder I've never spent more than five
minutes in these in these doctor's
office visits they don't ask about my
nutrition
um they don't ask about they hardly ask
about like my physical exercise I I
bring up all these things my supplement
intake my nutrition all these things and
it's like they're just waiting for me to
quit rambling so they can just tell me
that I'm depressed you know they're not
[ __ ] listening
and and it's the same thing that that
we're doing to ourselves we're not
listening we're not listening to
external input we're not listening to
like things that you know weird uh you
know mental health dudes with podcasts
tell you about like me you don't listen
to me but you also don't listen to
yourself you
you have to quiet down you have to you
have to get to a point where you can
hear what's going on but when you
constantly go go up move oh I can't do
that I dude I can't sit in a room by
myself like what are you talking about I
cannot sit in silence bro I cannot sit
in the car with nothing playing like all
these things you tell yourself that you
can't do that you don't do because that
ain't you well
what about the things you're doing don't
seem to be working for you you know what
what about that
you know what what if your relationships
are suffering
what if you're not able to show up for
your family members the way that you
want to do maybe you're not able to show
up for your kids for your wife in the
way that you want to do and what happens
here is we make ourselves feel guilty we
make ourselves feel inadequate in the
story that we're kind of told the story
that's like through the Zeitgeist of our
modern culture is kind of this like
like you're not good enough you know
you're not good enough because of these
things
and we [ __ ] feel that man and we feel
I think as men we feel so inadequate
like we're so aware man of
like as much as you know in the public
eye I think we put up our ego of like
I'm [ __ ] fine like I'm handling my
[ __ ] you know like we're good but I
think deep down I think we're very aware
of our inadequacies I think we're very
aware of like
God damn my mind is kicking my ass like
I [ __ ]
me and my baby was just crying and like
I hate that [ __ ] baby I hate it and
then we make ourselves feel so bad about
feeling these feelings of hate for a
baby because we weren't able to like
stay patient in that moment
we make ourselves feel bad and we label
ourselves I'm an impatient person I'm
not a good dad
instead of you know we label ourselves
like we just like you know some sort of
outside lens on the outside of the earth
just like oh that's who that person is I
just watched him do it that's who he is
that represents who he is like what are
you talking about man okay so you got a
little impatient with your child
so you're you're a little sleepy so
maybe you worked extra so you can pay
for the food to feed for that child
maybe
um you know maybe you got in an argument
with your significant other and so your
your patience is thin and you know the
baby just won't stop crying and you know
all these things we we label ourselves
like I'm a bad dad well no what happens
what we're supposed to do is we notice
the obvious things we don't have to this
isn't even like you need to read a book
and find out what's good and bad you
know what's good and bad dude you know
it you know that when you raise your
voice at your wife when you raise your
voice at your kid you feel you don't
feel good afterwards
even externally if you like double down
on that thing inside if you're not
bullshitting yourself which I mean
you've just heard me talk about it out
loud so you can no longer [ __ ]
yourself sorry surprise
just listen man you your inner
experience your inner truth is trying to
kind of guide you but you feel
that you need to keep this front keep
this armor on keep this it's like we're
constantly
it's like we're almost
taking care of
the version of ourselves that other
people see
and know
versus
how we truly truly feel right now and
like accepting how we truly truly feel
you know
men's mental health it's this crazy
I try to think about why it's so crappy
you know why is it so difficult for all
of these like why is there not only so
many men in suffering but like once
they're suffering
why do they have such trouble listening
like what was it about you know I tried
to think about
when I finally started kind of getting
better and started kind of starting
going for me it was just this
you know I was suicidal there were so
many years of just feeling like a
complete bag of dicks and just accepting
that and just like really trying to do
my external face the best I could but my
inside was just suffering and like you
get to a point where the anxiety man the
anxiety is tough because
you can try to hide your sadness and you
could put on a fake smile and you could
puff your chest out and you know even
though you don't have the correct
muscles to support it you can make it
look like your chest is out and you're
tough and all these things you know but
the anxiety will give you away when
you're not able to be calm in like
everyday instances you know you like
just something regular at work and you
start like getting anxious
um a lot of us so so I mean there's
different types of people I think
introverted people kind of um we turn
that anger at ourselves like me I'm very
mean to myself in these moments I'm very
disrespectful I'm very um
self-deprecating I'm very like I'm
apologetic externally like I'm so sorry
to inconvenience you guys with my you
know piece of [ __ ] mind uh but I'm just
mean to myself inside and there's other
people who
um It Hurts So immediately to feel those
things inside and they have so many
guards up against maybe you're one of
these people maybe have so many guards
up against feeling hurt and feeling
embarrassed about having anxiety or
feeling the anxiety even in the first
place that you boom you you project you
trampoline that bad feeling out to
someone else and you yell at someone you
externalize these things or you judge
someone you start talking [ __ ] about
somebody gossip and this is like women
do this a lot when they're feeling
something uncomfortable in themselves
this is when they're always gossiping
and we're like what the [ __ ] you talking
why do you care
a lot of times the thing that men do you
know maybe it's not just Universe I
think a lot of men just would bring it
inside man we shove it in there we're
like instead of looking for inadequacies
in other people and pointing them out
you know women do this a lot and I'm not
trying to talk [ __ ] about what I'm just
trying to give an example of how we
think differently
um and they gossip they're like oh
Cynthia did this and like I would never
do that it helps them understand who
they are and like gives them a position
in the hierarchy of of you know beings
and people in in in our um in our
civilization but
we bring it inside a lot of the times we
you know either we act out and we yell
or we freak out we have our anxiety
attack and we like tell it like it's you
know we know how we act when we're when
we're anxious it's not our proudest
moment we're like
you know we're barking orders that
people were like telling people no I
can't I need to I need to no I need this
and um
we're just trying to in that moment when
we're having anxiety attack or a panic
attack we're just trying to [ __ ]
breathe you know and we're in fight or
flight and our our heart is is elevated
in like all the cortisone levels are
through the roof and there's all these
things that are going on and we're just
trying to like find some grounding in
those moments you know and
you know like I said either you're doing
externally some people do it externally
some people do it internally you know
and sometimes the internal can start to
spill over and you just kind of become
like an anxious like mess out here you
know
I've been there plenty of times bro
um but you know the thing is
I keep saying you don't listen you're
not [ __ ] listening you know there'll
be a reoccurring thing I'm going to say
here and the thing is you're not
listening if you get to that spot all
the time and that's when you hit me up
and that's when you that's when you you
know think you could pull up the breath
work that's when you you know listen to
the YouTube that's when you
um you know these last straw moments you
wake up the next morning and you do your
best to not think about them have you
noticed that I get texts from people
late at night they've been drinking
they've been smoking they've been
um you know people are doing coke
um hit me up later tonight and they're
just they're looping their bad thoughts
and they're stuck and they're they can't
sleep because they're anxious because
they're just repeating that say they're
just
trying to solve it all in their head you
know and what's beautiful
these people hit me up and a lot of
times I'm able to offer you know I could
send a big old text I can send
YouTube videos I can send links I can
send meditations I can send podcasts I
can uh hey here's this book that changed
my life hey have you heard about this
guy I think he's kind of like up your
alley and he thinks like you I mean I'm
literally I have so much I love all this
stuff I'm so fascinated with it I have
been for so many years I have all these
different you know mental health hard
hitters that have different personality
types and they're you know more
masculine or more feminine or more
introverted or more extroverted or
they've had this life experience or they
do this or they're an extreme athlete or
they're a musician or whatever and it's
like so great because I can send like oh
dude you would you would resonate like
oh oh you have a military background and
so you understand kind of like the the
Mind Over Matter part
um you understand the grit you know I'll
send you a Dave and Goggins book you
know or maybe that's not working for you
maybe you're being too hard on yourself
and need something a little soft you
know I can send you
um you know like a nice female yoga
teacher or a meditation teacher you know
so we learn about all these things we
learn about all these like the breath
work the meditation the the
um
you know childhood trauma all this stuff
we learn about it we hear about it but
we don't really take action on it we
don't really indulge into it unless
we're in those moments of struggle have
you noticed that
people don't listen until they're
they're desperate and what I'm telling
you is you will not solve this if you
only address it when you're desperate if
you only address your anxiety when
you're anxious you will not solve it if
you only address your depression When
You're Feeling Extreme depressed you
will not solve it I'm telling you
look I'm someone who got obsessed with
this stuff I got obsessed I was at maybe
it's just how I work I'm I'm just I'm
just extreme I have to it just works for
me and it's it's completely changed my
life and now I'm on this like weird path
of I didn't plan on this I'm on this
path of like
I really want to help people in every
way that I can and I really think that I
you know and I have and and it's it's
it feels like very in right relationship
with me like all the things because I
I've just changed so much you know my
life
my life before a lot of these
experiences my life before learning
about my depression and my anxiety and
my myself like what what is a self and
what's what's soul mean what's it mean
to have a soul what's it mean to be a
human what are my thoughts where do
those come from what is this what's
going on who's Jake what does that even
mean you know like all these deep
contemplative thoughts I just got so
obsessed with them
um and and if if it fulfills me now to
like
I've learned real information man real
[ __ ] I've been to counselors I've been a
therapists I've been to doctors I've
been prescribed medication I think
I mean it a lot of it sucks let's be
honest like that's something that nobody
wants to say something that nobody wants
to say is that antidepressants are not
the only [ __ ] answer
it's frankly I think antidepressants are
terrible I think they suck
I think look I know a lot of people that
have been helped by them
I would hate for my opinion to stop
someone from going to the doctor to get
antidepressants like if you think like
that's where I'm at you're just about to
go in next week and you just heard me
rambling on about thinking depression or
antidepressant sucks you're like I'm not
going to do it like I don't want to
I I would
there's a lot of being careful in this
world with mental health
and I recognize that and I think it is
important but I think that we also dance
around [ __ ] and I think that men need
more direct to the point honestly I
think we dance around too much [ __ ] I
think I think a lot of grown male
people need like
they need another homie telling them
like bro you don't [ __ ] need
antidepressants you need to change your
situation you need to change what you're
doing the things you're doing are not
working out for you because you're not
proud of yourself you're ashamed of what
you're doing you're not meeting up to
the standards that you think you're able
to meet up to you're not showing up for
your life how you know you're able to
show up you know you're staying exactly
the same and wondering like
why everything sucks it's like you
haven't done anything differently
you don't
turn 18 and get a job or you know go to
college and get your perfect job and
like you get a wife and you have a kid
and like everything's all good and all
your problems are solved no that's not
how it works if you're suffering from
anxiety and depression right now do you
want your children to have the same
thing do you want them to grow up with
that well let me tell you
the world might have might have
convinced you that these things are like
genetic that where I'm just born this
way and for many years I was so afraid
of being a father for that like I was
like I'm not going to be a father and I
would lie to myself and really deep down
I was like I just don't want him to have
like a [ __ ] up mind like I have I've
just suffered so much and my mind is
just honestly crazy and it's been so
hard for me to work with it that I don't
want to bring a child into this world
and have them deal with that because
that just seems cruel that seems so
cruel to give them a brain anything like
mine I used to think that all the time
but you can listen to this guy Gabor
mate uh g-a-b-o-r
um I think it's just m-a-t-e amongst
just so many other there's just so many
good podcasts on mental health and stuff
these days but really I've learned that
a lot of this stuff is not genetics
genetics we actually misunderstand
genetics a lot you know epigenetic
expression is something that's huge your
experiences are what
um turn on certain genes you know your
life
as a young person being traumatized
going through like very traumatic
experiences
um those are more of what shape you than
being born a certain way you know that
that's something that we really need to
shake is
like right now if you're listening to my
voice and you have it in your like like
let me talk to these pieces of you
please
that think that you're like this forever
that think that you were born this way
like you're just so [ __ ] like you got
a bad one you're you got a bad body
like you were
you're you're the whole rest of your
life is gonna have to be to suffer
because well you just got a shitty one
that's not true that is not true and the
way genetics work that you know you can
look into epigenetics and it gets really
pseudosciency very quick and it gets
very woo-woo but uh there's a lot of
fantastic information that really helps
us understand ourselves and it makes us
feel a little more in control of our
actions that you know we can see lead to
these feelings of depression and anxiety
and stuff so firstly let me just say
I'll bring it around again you know if
you're at a point where you need
antidepressants and you're like this is
this is I'm suffering so bad that like
I've tried all these other things and I
don't I
like please do it you know it's not
forever but I would also invite you to
really learn about these things outside
of what the doctor is telling you the
doctor has incentives and in
it's just a whole mess you know I I
think the thing that happens with our
with our Modern Health Care is the
second that
like if you have depression your next
step watch what we do
if you can't you admit that you have
depression I'm depressed I'm anxious you
tell somebody
all right well let's get you into the
doctor man it's okay like they're you
know they kind of come from a place of
love and support if you tell a family
member whatever they're like cool all
right well let's make you a doctor
appointment
um
and I'm not saying that that's bad like
I hope that you're reading between the
lines as much as you can here
I think a therapist appointment
is please like yes oh man yes right away
as soon as you can whether it's you know
they have better help and all this stuff
but like as far as I'm concerned if you
can get yourself physically in front of
a person
um
you know you can really connect and
really understand each other and I
really think I mean dude even just the
conversation of talking to another
person it could be a male or a female or
young or older whatever just get to a
therapist they're not going to solve all
your problems from for you they're not
going to give you all the answers you're
not going to go to therapy a couple
times and be like uh I'm totally better
now I'm completely happy and I'm going
to be happy until I die no no life is a
process life is this whole thing is
consistent work and the more you learn
now the more you could suffer less those
same you can stop tripping on the same
curbs that you've been tripping on for
years like that you've convinced
yourself that this is who I am and this
is how my brain works and this is the
structure of My reality that's not
[ __ ] true you can learn new
information you could change your future
by this you can change the way that your
mind is going to work in the future and
no I'm not saying that like everybody
with mental health issues just needs to
do mind over matter and read a couple
you know listen to a couple podcasts and
you'll be cured I'm not saying that but
I think that we we really put an anchor
around our ankles we really just man we
lock ourselves up with this [ __ ] we feel
the second that we're if we admit that
we have depression we're like we need to
go to the doctor okay
doesn't it I mean you know you know when
you go to the hospital you know when you
go to the doctor's office it's when you
have an injury
a physical injury that like
and I know I talked about like you know
depression you know you see a broken leg
but you don't see depression but it's
still kind of in the same ballpark
that's true but
what are your actions that led up to
that
that's a huge thing and careful because
you're going to make yourself feel
guilty right away like don't do that
don't make yourself feel shameful that's
not what this is about this is looking
at what's going on and causation
correlation you know this is
okay it's it's 5 P.M
I feel [ __ ] sad
I feel so much shitty I'm just thinking
about my whole life I'm like I haven't
[ __ ] accomplished anything I'm
inadequate I Stumble over my words I've
been on the same job for two years I
don't really see like
you know all these things say it's 5 p.m
it's later in the day and that's when
you're feeling the depression
things are slowing down whatever you had
to do that day you know it's slowing
down you got to look at what did you do
that day though
what were the actions that you took as a
biomechanical
you know structure here
did you wake up in the morning and get
vitamin D on your skin you know before
11 A.M there's science on that you know
uh getting it resets your circadian
rhythm
um it's going to release all these
chemicals what was your breakfast like
are you eating a bunch of carbs carbs
are going to make you feel like you're
digesting a lot everybody has very
different reactions with food but
nowadays honestly I think that our our
modern culture has really destroyed our
stomachs and our insides that I mean
like like we can't process these seed
oils that are in everything so it's like
what what did you eat that day
how much did you eat did you over
indulge did you make decisions with that
food that makes you feel proud of
yourself what did you consume did you
wake up and did you go on social media
did you spend an hour on Tick Tock
living other people's lives or
concentrating on what other people want
you to talk about
um you know did you did you wake up and
you do something that you're passionate
about did you put your phone away and
you you set aside 15 minutes to play
with your dog
did you
it's 5 p.m are you on your phone at
dinner right now
is your daughter over there on an iPad
and you're not having a conversation
with her you know
a lot of the way we feel if you're
feeling sad at 5 PM right
you have to look at what you did that
day you have to look what you did that
week that month are you going towards
your goals do you have any goals there's
this thing man
we don't talk about it much because it
seems like this like like the
Philosopher's Stone of only people who
are on the search for enlightenment you
care about meaning in in being someone
every single human has a desire for
meaning we need meaning we need purpose
if we're not living up to ourselves if
we're just playing video games all day
if we're not showing up to
um you know if we're not taking our wife
on dates if we're not buying her flowers
if we're not
um being silly if we're not being fun if
we're not being a joy for other people
to be around in turn making us a joy for
ourselves to be around if we're not
working on our passions if we're not
um proud of ourselves if we're not
pushing ourselves you know say you're
not a creative person say that you don't
really have things that you sit around
at home and you know you don't like
painting you don't like making music
you're like
um writing poetry you know these things
you don't have to do those things like
what about working on your car what
about working on a project car what
about
um
uh you know maybe you've been an athlete
your whole life maybe you like love
working out are you a part of any sort
of gym Community do you have Bros that
you at least like give a fist bump that
you walk into the gym because you've
been going there for a few months you
kind of recognize the same sort of
people
um do you have a routine that works out
for you do you have a way that is
setting up your like biochemical suit
here to succeed well so you know the
food you eat the um the the items you
drink the supplements you take or you
don't take the um the content that you
consume the amount of caffeine that
you're consuming you know all of these
things that we do everything that we do
throughout the day is our experience of
who we are you know we we're always
fueling who this person is like dude
maybe you feel sad at 5 p.m because you
haven't done anything today towards your
purpose towards being happy towards
serving your wife towards serving your
daughter towards serving your son
towards taking care of your dog towards
you know you didn't play with your cat
you didn't
you have to life has meaning because we
we siphon for it we we dig for meaning
you know it's right here but we also
gotta dig for it we gotta try for it I
think that we live in this Wally World
of of
consuming man we're not doing like
really really think about if you're
sitting on your phone for hours a day
and you're just
you just like this is all you're doing
and you're consuming this stuff and
maybe it's good stuff maybe there's some
good stuff and then maybe some cool
facts like tell me how many you remember
that's a thing but
you're not doing anything you're
it's like you're a battery or something
you know have you become a battery to
other people's agendas
have you been are you a part of a
someone else's system
and you go to work every day and you
feed their dreams and you put money in
their pocket and you get just enough
money to get by but you're drained and
you're tired and your body [ __ ] hurts
at the end of the day and you don't have
enough energy to like do anything or
fulfill yourself or like you know write
a few lines of poetry or or work on your
project car outside or reorganize the
garage or paint the kitchen or like
these things that are like fulfilling
and nice and it feels good to like get
these things done and we feel like we're
moving forward with them you know if you
don't have any energy for that because
you just gave all of your energy during
the day to someone else like of course
you're going to feel sad dude
and the answer is it
the answer isn't found in just like a
new job
um in a new work environment
it's found in what you put action into
you know you have to give yourself
something that that makes you enthralled
to wake up in the morning and that's a
tough one because that really seems like
it shouldn't be something we do right it
seems like we should wake up
and like ah I love my life and that's
why I'm happy
but no I think the truth of it is more
so you wake up
and
whatever your mind is saying whatever's
left over from the dream world whatever
you know arguments we're still having
from the day before
when you wake up in the morning man you
gotta insert who you want to be
and
actually I think we should stick on this
for a second because
I think
my life
so another way that I was always a
victim is
I always would say like man I don't get
how people wake up in a good mood you
know every morning I wake up and it's
turmoil
like I wake up and it's just
there's the nihilistic thoughts there's
the feelings of inadequacy
there's the oh it just checked in on my
body my body still hurts figures
you know
it's like we we have these it's like say
you have like 10 thoughts as soon as you
wake up
oh we have so many much more in that
like our our brains are just throwing
millions of thoughts a day but say you
have 10 thoughts when you wake up and
they're all negative and they're all
like here's who I am and I suck and I'm
going to this job that I hate and it's
like you're just reassuring
who you think yourself to be
but you could change that story
for me
I would wake up
and honest this man is seriously it's
like eyes open
in you know eyes open here piece of [ __ ]
ah living sucks living is hard
everything you do is difficult
everything is heavy it's like I like I
don't choose to think these thoughts you
know but it's like it seems like every
time I you know I wake up open my eyes
and I come out of the dream world and
I'm just like oh my God was I just being
tortured in my dreams what the [ __ ] was
going on
and it feels like
it feels like you just played like like
you played football all night in your
brain and your body is so tired
sometimes like sometimes you'll have
like some energy you know
but the the
like the churning of the meanness is
still going in your head
so let me just say like as someone who
has been there [ __ ] man I'm sorry that
that sucks I'm really sorry that that
happens
I'm really sorry man that that when you
wake up
your brain is mean to you
I'm sorry dude that sucks
and
I know that it probably seems like
you're probably one in a billion for
being like that you probably think
you're like some sort of weird freak or
something
you know because your brain is just you
know negative and complaining right when
you open your eyes like dude
of course your day is going to be hard
you're fighting with this dude all day
it's exhausting It's Just Gonna Keep
compounding by the end of the day now
you have the day before his tiredness
and it just keeps stacking and of course
you've got anxiety about that things
start to get heavy and your arms start
to feel a little more weak than they
should
yeah dude
so firstly like I'm sorry I'm sorry that
you feel that way because it it's it's
real and man I could resonate with that
so much it always felt like it took me
hours to even
like be functioning in the morning or
you know I had to like put on this like
crazy put on the mask right away and
it's like trying to shove that [ __ ] back
down there it tried to come up when you
were sleeping that pain that trauma that
feeling of an adequacy that
um the thing I did years ago that I'm
still so guilty about even though I know
damn well that I'm not that same person
anymore and I was just working off you
know
I don't think that way anymore but I'm
still going to try to make myself feel
guilty about it every single day it's
like bro you learned a lesson let it go
it's done
let it be whatever you got to do to let
that thing go like if if in this
specific example if you have something
that you're guilty or shameful about
that you did years ago or you did when
you were younger or that you didn't do
when you years ago you didn't do when
you were younger or where you're at
guilt shame it's man that's a sticky one
right let me tell you
it's okay for one because
you not that
right you're not that
you're not just that one thing are you
kidding me man if you're gonna say this
one mistake I made is who I am like what
about everything that you've done
outside of that what about all the dope
[ __ ] you've done you've done like what
about every time you you know someone
ran out of gas and you ran him a gas can
or you helped someone fix their car or
um you held the door open or you had a
conversation with your little brother or
you helped your aunts out or you did the
dishes after Thanksgiving dinner or you
I mean there's all these and I'm not
even just saying like Good Deed stuff
there's a million things all day that we
do that you know there's no reason to
feel ashamed about and and you know
maybe we can feel a little proud of
ourselves for you know if we're a lesser
man the day before and now we're we're
doing these things that we didn't get
done the day before we'd feel proud of
ourselves so you need to be able to look
at where you're at and look how far
you've come and go you know what I'm
doing okay because likely dude you're
probably doing okay if you're listening
to this [ __ ] right now you're doing okay
you are in the process of helping
yourself you're not not admitting any
longer that you don't have to pressure
anxiety you faced it you're like [ __ ]
what's what do they say in the um uh the
12-step program is is you know the first
step is admitting you have a problem and
a lot of this depression anxiety stuff
as much as I like I love to really
pinpoint on like don't call yourself a
depressed person don't call yourself an
anxious person like you're just a person
experiencing the human emotion of
anxiousness everybody's got that feeling
don't identify with it don't buckle down
on it but if you can if you can
if you can
just
not identify with it
and just experience it as a human
experiencing these things
and go okay you know create a little
distance you got to create a little
distance is the thing you got to create
a little because you're the Observer of
thoughts right you're not your thoughts
we all have intrusive thoughts you know
I had a actually had a nice conversation
with them with Ricky Hall on my podcast
you know year it's actually been years
now
um but she was talking about intrusive
thoughts and I feel like I at the time I
remember kind of just discovering about
wow I'm not such a piece of [ __ ] like
everybody kind of has intrusive thoughts
and like you just don't act on them and
it's okay like it doesn't mean you're
bad person doesn't mean you're you know
intrinsically evil deep down you know uh
you know it's it's like
intrusive thoughts are are
part of being a human in the things that
you're doing the things you're consuming
might be adding to those you know
um I think if you are a nihilistic kind
of like
I'm gonna guess I can picture kind of
like a mean bully you know negative kind
of uh anti-social sort of person if that
person is listening to just like a ton
of dark comedy and is feeling their hate
then their internal voice might be like
a comedic version of mean you know and I
think that's something worth being
careful about um at the beginning when I
started doing all this mental health
stuff because I really like dark comedy
um uh I really love like the nihilism
I've really loved like the
um I guess I'll go kill myself now like
it was that sort of like weird
I realized at some point that that was
actually like very not helping me like
it was really contributing to my
internal talk my self-talk was just very
negative and very mean to myself and it
was a lot of that sort of I was using
jokes as a way to to write it off and it
was actually kind of a very serious
thing I mean you're joking about
murdering yourself that's [ __ ]
serious just because you're laughing
doesn't mean that it's it's not serious
so um at the beginning for me I actually
I think I stopped consuming like
everything that wasn't crazy positive
like I oh yeah I did I uh I actually
literally even cut off friends
um if I was in group messages I was in
um you know friendships that
like if we just set funny memes back and
forth I'm done if we just
um if you're gossiping to me I'm done if
you're going to be negative I'm done
um
yeah I was just I was like I can't
there's so much darkness in my mind I
need to start shoving some light in
that's kind of like where I was so
apologies for the sound of me sipping my
coffee weirdly hopefully wearing
headphones so it sounds like I'm sipping
it like right in your
oh
I hope you're actually at the gym right
now
we're at a stoplight
and you have to just listen to me I'm
gonna do it again
anyway this podcast sucks
um
man uh yeah at the beginning I was
basically rejecting everything like I
was uh I was like if it's not going to
Aid my mental health
if it's not going to fix me
I'm not doing it you know
um
and so there is lines in that there is
you know like what I just said if they
can't fix me I would like to point out
that
this self-help stuff can get
dangerous isn't the right word but it
can get um
um consuming
I don't think it's really something for
everybody to worry about I think it's
something for people to worry about who
are in the mental health Sphere for like
years and years but um I think there's a
thing Alan Watts calls the backwards law
n watts is a philosopher that I really
like
um he has a thing called backwards law
which is basically
when you are
in a place of lack
when you're saying
I need to do these things to get better
I'm sick so in order to get better I
need to meditate I'm sick
I'm disgusting I'm broken
so in order to be not broken
I need to do this thing
the backwards law Alan Watts expresses
that by putting yourself in a position
of someone being
you know a victim or someone being in a
place of of lack of not having something
you're actually exacerbating so it's
like like think about it if you
if you were fulfilled and happy within
your being you would not be looking for
fulfillment and happiness out there why
would you you already have those things
you know
I I think this really I hope that this
can thread into what I was saying at the
beginning about not identifying as being
a depressed person or not identifying as
I have anxiety I'm an anxious person
I think that gets us stuck I think that
um I think that keeps us in a cycle you
know it look if that's where you're at
and this is all like way too much and
it's way too just dense and it's like
like you're just like man what okay so
suddenly I I thought I had depression
and now you're telling me that I don't
have depression I'm not someone who has
depression maybe it gets a little too
too deep for you quickly you'll
understand this soon but
if you if you're putting yourself in a
position of lack of not having something
you're kind of like asking the universe
in a way to like reaffirm that in in a
strange sense
um
you know
they talk about in um in like the Law of
Attraction and stuff if you've heard of
any of that
kind of like you gotta like you know
they say you gotta Envision it and you
you
um you in in your mental mind you kind
of like see your dream life and you see
you living it and you and you visualize
and all these things
um and if you've ever actually done
these things if you've ever done any
sort of like law of attraction or like
manifestation meditation if you give
into it I mean especially if you do it
like for a few weeks where you really
like let your ego guards down man you
get these like biochemical like you're
you'll sit there in these meditations
and you'll be just squirming and you've
got chills through your whole body and
like in your mind's eye like in in your
head like you're visualizing you know in
your imagination you are seeing yourself
you know doing these things and like oh
cool I've got this cool red sports car
and I got this nice big house or
whatever it is that you're trying to you
know manifest but um
the thing about it though that I've
learned over like you know a few years
of this sort of stuff like my perception
of the Law of Attraction has changed
because you know at first I thought it
was like total weird and then there was
a few months of me like this is the
absolute truth and this is how reality
works and then I was like okay let's get
a little distance from it started kind
of like understanding a little bit more
um the trick to the law of attraction is
living the moment as if it were here and
now so like if you were
in a place if you were on a beach and
you're relaxed and like think about all
the background tasks that you can have
shut so say you're on a beach you
relaxed you're married you're happy with
your wife your child is healthy
um you have all the money in the bank
that you need you fine on finances your
work is okay your family's healthy
everything there's no like fires to put
out right now you've you've you've been
organized leading up to this you know
like like you guys know how good
vacation Works to get up to the vacation
you gotta dot your tees you gotta cross
your eyes you know
um uh you gotta you gotta make sure that
things at home are good to enjoy this
vacation you've got to make sure that
did I leave the [ __ ] did I leave the
water on to leave the oven on you know
like you can't have those background
tasks or else you're unable to be
present to where you are
so what you do with this Law of
Attraction when you like visualize
yourself in these positions
um and it it's kind of difficult your
first few times it really does kind of
take some work this is the thing that
you can practice and actually gain skill
on
but you visualize these things you
visualize yourself at the beach and like
maybe you're going to think about all
the background tasks it's like cool I
didn't leave the oven on my family's
healthy my baby's healthy you know or
you're gonna like look and see oh I have
a healthy baby I have a beautiful wife I
have my dog is playing fetch this sunset
is beautiful what starts to happen
In This Moment you're sitting there in
your in your living room or whatever in
your bedroom and you're visualizing
yourself be at the beach you start to
your body actually starts to take over
these your body has these chemical
responses of like relaxing you seriously
feel like you're there and this might
seem kind of like a cool little trick
but it's actually very profound like
really think about the the the details
of this this is the like the
if you can In This Moment visualize
yourself elsewhere
and feel it like it's here and now
like the way that
it's not like you're going to get a
knock on your front door and someone
hands you the keys of the Ferrari that
you just visualize in your head you know
what I mean but when you can get
yourself in the mindset
of
feeling that that's real in a real sense
of like
you know what
I can kind of see what happens when we
visualize things when we use like Law of
Attraction manifestation stuff when we
visualize a future for ourselves
you know a lot of it's maybe grandiose
maybe it's like you know more money than
we think we could really make or more
you know bigger house and and all these
things but you really actually
when you do it for a few weeks you do
for even a couple days sometimes like
you you can start to actually see the
steps in your life now from right where
you're at in physical reality right here
without the manifestation without the
thinking mind
you start to
a little bit of like a staircase or like
a bridge starts to kind of build between
where you're at and that thing in in
some senses you know and when you can
kind of like consistently remind
yourself about it like really like what
would it feel like to allow myself to
have those things like what kind of
person would I be like if those things
would be happening you know what what
who who would I be for that to be real
and when you put yourself in that
position when you put yourself in that
mindset it's kind of like
it becomes more real for one and so your
everyday life is kind of like this
little instances you know of of like you
might meet people or shake hands with
people or like see things on on signs or
like
be in certain places in certain times
that you probably wouldn't have noticed
might be in the direction of your future
self of your future goal because you
were so actually caught up in just like
thinking who you are now or who you've
been in the past and like oh I'm just
sad person it's like when you can't see
a way out you're gonna just keep looping
you know and I'm not saying that like
the only way you know I'm certainly not
saying the the way out of depression is
to is to sit down and manifest your
beautiful life but I think that there is
a
there is something to be said about
getting ourselves out of fight or flight
um I think a lot of us are walking
around seriously at all times even when
we're dreaming in a state of
tense
you know in in that tension turns into
armor and it turns into our personality
there's this guy Dr Joe dispenza
um which I mean if if you love this like
we like woo-woo manifestation Law of
Attraction stuff if that Sparks you and
like you're really ready to you know
what I got a couple months I'm going to
go ham on this I'm feeling motivated I
would recommend Joe dispenza honestly
like his sub he has meditation Retreats
he has books um he is someone who if you
get obsessed with him I think that you
really could truly change your reality
um you know I'll let you dive into that
but Dr Joe dispenza he says some things
that are very profound there's another
one that's you know there's some
pseudoscience mixed in there there's
some stuff that's a little weird but
there's a lot of stuff that man we just
listen it's it's pretty profound so he
says this thing
um ah
a thought becomes
an action or no oh no a thought becomes
a mood a mood becomes
a personality
something like that man I butchered it
but basically you know a thought when we
hold on to this thing like this person
wronged me this person did this thing
God damn it they suck and then we hold
on to that for more than like a day like
it doesn't just it doesn't just use its
time like all right I had my four
minutes of being pissed off about it and
now it's my job as a grown ass man to
take care of business okay cool that
person rear-ended me like Damn it that
sucks oh not yeah my whole day is
inconvenienced yeah I'm gonna have to
you know my insurance and my car in a
couple yeah there's all those things
cool well let's deal with it you know
when you
when you can take yourself out of
man I'm getting I'm getting into more
Corner painting like I'm I suddenly
realize that like maybe I'm not being as
useful as I could be when I'm explaining
these things I I want to speak to
everybody I want to really speak to the
I I don't want to
I remember my dad
my dad was a drug addict
and
I remember when I was like eight or nine
we had like lost the house we had been
evicted
um
you know just sleeping at like neighbors
houses and stuff and my dad was just
like just on meth
and
he like finally agreed my mom got him to
agree to like go to rehab right
and I remember dude he went for a couple
days
if that
I remember he called
and it was like this devastating thing
for my mom because I feel like she was
probably like wow he's going to rehab
like we might be able to fix this whole
thing
he calls and he's just
this [ __ ] ain't for me they're talking
to people who are alcoholics I'm not an
alcoholic never had a problem with
drinking my life you know this [ __ ] is
wasting my time you know
any um I remember he had I
it's funny I remember this very visually
I think because it was probably a
devastating thing to my mother and I was
probably trying to like read her energy
and try to understand the situation it
was a very confusing situation for me as
a young child anyway because there was a
I was aware of the truth but I was also
aware of um nobody saying the truth and
I'm like what the [ __ ] are adults are
crazy I was I was every adult I
interacted with was seriously nutty I
did not understand how anybody saw the
world but um
my I remember he came back and he had
like this like uh I think he spent some
time in the the military when he was
over he had like this like military
green sack and it had all his stuff in
him
I don't know if he like got dropped off
by the bus or what
he's just like all angry and he was just
he was just storming off you know and um
I don't know
the thing is
he left rehab because they're talking
about alcohol and he doesn't have a
problem with alcohol
and he wasn't patient he wasn't
listening
he was listening to
to his story of himself more than he was
just shutting up and listening to the
people and that you know the rehab
Circle or whatever it was
because
you know when you're suffering
when you're suffering yourself
especially when you're making things
worse than they need to be unknowingly
and I'm not saying this to make you feel
guilty don't you dare feel guilty about
it it's part of The Human Experience
something that now that I mentioned
you've heard someone talk about it you
can notice and go oh man I was making my
feels myself feel shameful for it was
adding all this extra weight on this
problem that I already had I don't need
to do that man that's part of being a
man to be honest sorry
um but you know if my dad would have
just [ __ ] listened if he would have
just listened if he would have just sat
down and listened like give it a couple
days I mean he probably couldn't hear
because he's got Methodist system you
know he's he's probably like imagine
this man tried to sit down in a circle
like listen to people go I'm I'm James
I'm an alcoholic and you know and like I
can't help it but I just love four Locos
and you know whatever so his thing is
you know my dad's just like
fancy just hunt you know I don't know I
don't think that I could sit in a rehab
meeting if I was um had methamphetamine
in my system either but I don't know man
I think I'm using this as an example of
you gotta you gotta [ __ ] listen
because if he would have just listened
if he would have just sat still and you
know maybe maybe in this analogy it's
bad because
he had a drug in a system that is not
going to allow you to sit down and like
at some point you gotta like let the
drug work its way out and then you can
start hearing but
um maybe you got a drug in your system
maybe you've got maybe your drug is is
you know
maybe it's booze maybe it's weed maybe
it's coke maybe it's too much caffeine
maybe it's energy drinks maybe it's
Adderall maybe it's not even a substance
maybe it's not even anything you're
consuming maybe your drug is like your
continuous [ __ ] Loops of inadequacy
maybe your drug is self-pity maybe your
drug is feeling sorry for yourself maybe
your drug is massive victimization maybe
your drug is over catastrophic
maybe your drug is not knowing how to
use words properly maybe your your drug
is a over catastrophizing things you
know that's something that I'd always do
is I always look at the whole staircase
rather than just this what's this one
stay right here that I can take I'm
trying to solve the problem of getting
you know there's a staircase going into
the clouds and I'm like I can't handle
that well of course you can't handle
that you knucklehead you have wings
but you can't handle one step at a time
so whatever your drug is
and we've all got them and don't feel
guilty about it and you know as far as
let me just say external drugs what a
time to be alive there's a lot of
amazing drugs like have you ever tried
ecstasy and Molly holy crap like no
wonder that people are addicted to drugs
they feel great and there's such a
difference from how we feel continuously
you know this life is just go go go go
more next more next go you're gonna
arrive and the suddenly we get older and
we're like oh my God I didn't stop and
slow down and I had all these things
that were just attacking me from the
inside that I could have dissipated long
ago damn it you know
um you know we live in a world of of
beautiful colors and dopamine triggers
and everything's built like a slot
machine and I mean look at like Dr
Pepper 23 flavors because they have
science they they hired scientists
this is not that profound but the hired
scientists to all right what are the
feelings on your tongue that like give
you flavor sensation they release
chemicals that go ah good I like this
yeah you know that comes from finding
fruit which was very few and far between
over evolutionary process and now that's
gamed against us the 23 flavors on our
tongue are you know we have these
it's difficult man it's difficult out
here there's a lot of good [ __ ] beer is
delicious
I mean you know come on it's nothing to
feel guilty about but
if you notice that the things you're
addicted to whether it's external things
external validation whether it's
internal things internal suffering
internal thought patterns internal
feelings of inadequacy these stories
that we're telling ourselves this person
we think ourselves to be at this
continuous loop of [ __ ] in our heads
if we're addicted to it and it's not
serving us if it's if it's not
the thing is if you're doing things that
are no longer serving you
what are you doing
that's what's going on man maybe you're
doing things that aren't serving you
maybe you're not living in the way that
you think that you should be living in
the way that you want to be living and
the way that you know you're worthy of
living you know it's it's like there's a
this movie the Freedom Writers and they
have this quote and I remember man I
used to think about this quote so much
and I thought I understood it and I
actually I had a new perception of it
later in life but uh I think it's
Freedom Writers I mean it's Dead Poets
Society it's our greatest fear is not
that we are inadequate our greatest fear
is that we are powerful beyond measure
and
man
that's a that's a
I think for men I think for the
masculine
like not just our role in society but
like how our minds work dude like how
our ship functions
I think
like at the core of life itself I think
that this is something that is like part
of us that we can't deny I think we have
to have
we have to have meaning we have to have
each of us has something to offer the
world
and it doesn't have to be like a public
like on a stage or I'm an actor or I
made this movie or I made a ton of money
or like dude there's just like a level
of showing up for your life and only the
way that you can that if you're not
doing it every day
you start to suffer there's a thing this
is like a this is a this is like if
you're aliens studying the humans this
is something that happens I'm telling
you a lot of our suffering and a lot of
our pain you know we talk about
childhood trauma and we talk about um uh
you know people even talk about like
generational trauma or like karmic
experiences that they're unwinding you
know all these things
like yeah it's all that it's all that
there's these things that like you can
put a marker on and like okay I can
solve that I can reach that like okay
that thing that happened with my dad
when I was younger
man I think that is affecting me so like
okay I could dive into that and I can
start writing about that and I can free
write and you know nobody's gonna read
it but you know you get it out of your
head you start writing it you start
talking to yourself you record yourself
and you listen back to it or you don't
even listen back to it you just get it
out nobody has to hear it nobody has to
see it nobody has to read it it starts
to kind of like solve itself but the
thing is what we do and don't feel
guilty or shameful about this what we do
is we don't look at those things because
they're going to go against who we think
ourselves to be if you are feeling
experience if you're feeling weak on the
inside but your external view of how the
world sees you and the person you put
out the person your wife knows you as is
is is the tough guy the strong guy the
guy that can handle everything like
you're going to have things that you
deny like you're going to have these
things in your head of
um I mean I imagine like a military guy
a military guy
I mean man they're really made to shove
it down they're really made to like mind
over matter in this strange way I think
there's like a softer mind over matter
that could be um studied and not so much
like the David Goggins of like get your
[ __ ] together you know there's a there's
a mindfulness uh mind over matter of
like
quieting down and refusing to interact
with any thoughts that come up and it
brings this quiet that like Intuition or
like some people would call like God
starts to kind of um
it's not like you hear voices you know
it's like you hear like an external
voice other than your own it's kind of
just like before the intellect
intellectualization before the thought
patterns before the the the
personhood is injected into it there's
this listening that you can do that
um
makes you feel like in in right
relationship with your life I just I
just think that this is like at the core
of being a human and it's something
we're not really taught to be honest
with you a lot of um like spiritual
stuff a lot of religious texts a lot of
this sort of like that whole world
there's we threw out a lot of baby with
the bath water like to be a functioning
human a lot of our internal
psychological experience like these
other civilizations before us before
like now where we're at before just like
the science way of thinking
they explore these same things like
we're not the first generation to suffer
man like they there's all this crazy
good knowledge and you gotta get you
know a lot of it's it's in different
it's in different um um you know not
languages but like it's a different time
frame like look at look at 10 years ago
how much our slang has changed look at
look at 15 years ago like the way we
talk the way look at I'm a I'm a um uh
oh my God I just forgot I'm a millennial
um in in gen Z and lower like the words
that they use like they're just flame
lit fire dead ass
um like you know like just the the lingo
that just you know within 10 years it's
just so difficult to understand imagine
hundreds of years thousands of years and
different interpretations and different
ways of using language and and uh you
know like if there was all these fires
or something or there's all this
knowledge that was lost from these
ancient books of religion and
spirituality and and you know knowledge
of the self and philosophy and these
sorts of things and it gets retold and
what what I'm saying I think is um is
there's crazy good knowledge and a lot
of this stuff but you have to you know
don't be a dick don't be like I don't
get this [ __ ] it ain't me like don't be
just chill out you know just stop being
such a hard ass and just listen to the
stuff and maybe it's not the way that
you talk maybe it's not the way that you
think but if you just sit and listen to
it and get yourself out of the way you
know like stop being if you're sitting
there listening to an audiobook or
listening to a YouTube lecture and
you're sitting there going this ain't
this is [ __ ] I don't think this like
I mean you're disagreeing with that
information
but
I I don't understand if you if what
you're doing is not working out
clearly it's not working out admit that
it's not working out the things you're
doing are not working for you so it's
time to do something different
you listen do you hear that you have to
do something different brother
you have to learn new information and
you don't have to you know like maybe
you're going to start reading the Bible
in private you don't have to go get a
throat tattoo of a cross man you don't
have to you don't have to go to church
you have to tell people you don't have
to you know I'm not even just saying
religion I'm saying like this whole
mental health sphere like if you search
Man Ted Talks 15 to 20 minute 10 you
know 11 to 20 minute whatever they are
TED Talks
profoundly can change your life
profoundly will make you see yourself in
ways you never saw yourself before but
you're sitting there you're sitting
there too busy to listen to a TED Talk
you're sitting there like this dude
[ __ ] talks weird like oh he's a
Canadian oh this guy is a oh he's
wearing a Patriots jersey I don't [ __ ]
with the Patriots this guy has nothing
to say like stop being a tribalistic
idiot how about that
stop being such a dumb ape how about
that
and listen to these people listen to
this information listen to me damn it
listen to me I had a gun against my
temple years ago man and I'm literally
I'm publicly on a podcast I almost have
a hundred episodes of a of a you know
kind of mental health based podcast
because I was suffering so bad and I
discovered I was able to have some
switch flip in me of of
learning all these things like dude who
I am now is so vastly different from the
person I was years ago I mean I I
listened to so much information about
this I've read so much information about
mental health and psychology and like my
entire experience of the world is
completely different and I will say I
would like to point out I'm not cured
I'm not happy all the time
I'm
more comfortable in my body
more confident in who I am you know I
still have a ton of neuroticism in in in
in
um you know like I said I was I wake up
in the mornings and like I said
sometimes it's negative a lot of times
probably most of the time it's negative
but what I do is I insert these good
things
in the mornings I don't listen to I
don't I don't social media [ __ ] I
don't listen to uh whatever is on the
radio I don't listen to whatever is on
TV I don't want to like find the sixth
rerun of the office and watch it in the
morning because it makes me feel
comfortable I want to if I wake up in
the morning and my brain is saying mean
things I'm gonna say nah not today
no and I'm not going to shove them down
but I'm going to say nah not today
what do you really mean is that true
like a friend like a Stern friend you
know I wake up in the morning and if my
mind is saying you're inadequate you're
tired uh those dreams that you have
those things that you want to accomplish
next year like you're an idiot for even
like
like where what are you even talking
about like the like were you living in a
fairy tale land
he has all these things that like I
could do all this work on Tuesday and I
could go to bed just feeling like man I
really accomplished a lot I feel like I
fed my brain so well I think I'm on
track you know I have these goals I want
to accomplish at work I have these goals
I want to accomplish in my personal life
and man I really feel like I'm on track
and you close your eyes and you wake up
in the morning and your mind is like
you're a big fat piece of [ __ ]
and it's like what and the thing is what
you got to do and what I do now
is I laugh at that
oh you think so bruh and like it
sometimes laugh isn't even real you know
like sometimes like this positive person
that I insert in the morning does not
feel real that's a huge part of this
when you're depressed you're gonna do a
lot of [ __ ] to get out of it that feels
fake it feels contrived it feels made up
it feels like you feel silly as a
[ __ ] if someone's watching you
do these things if you're uh like
married or you have a girlfriend or
um if you don't live alone in your
apartment like I do if you have if you
have anybody watching you
um you're going to feel so silly
but trust me
when you start to
it's not so much that you put on the
boxing gloves and you get into the ring
with those thoughts in the morning
recognizing them is the hugest thing and
when you can reckon and when you could
when you talk back to them when you like
have a conversation with yourself
internally or even like say it out loud
please say it out loud try that Lily
start talking to yourself out loud in
these moments that's beautiful please do
that
but
it almost like doesn't deny them because
a lot of what we're doing right now like
I mean I I don't know man I don't know
where you're at but if you're listening
to this
you might be in a crazy state of denial
you might be denying that you are
feeling such depression you might be
like I said you know we push these
things away because they're painful and
then
we break class and it we break glass in
case of emergency because it comes back
up you start having a panic attack
you're like what the [ __ ]
all this stuff it's like
it's like you forgot to batten down the
hatch you know properly and so like the
oil
of you know your inadequacy and like who
you think yourself uh you know not to be
and what you know it starts to well up
it starts to kind of like leak out and
you're like oh [ __ ] oh no you start to
panic and you start you know not being
yourself or you act out or you protect
your ego or you know your ego protects
what it thinks it is
um you know you you have to
I used to say this thing in the morning
let's get this bread and it's so silly
but I actually did this for many years
um
I actually still say it sometimes
um I have I'm a strange person in the
morning now that I'm realizing
um I I would wake up and like open your
eyes your alarm goes off or it doesn't
whatever
you're tempted to like check through all
of your emails you're tempted to check
through all of your social media you're
tempted to scroll through social media
for a few minutes you're tempted to hit
snooze
I'm telling you these things are harming
your life your actions the first 15
minutes when you wake up seriously huge
um wake up
turn off your alarm
and there's this Mel Robbins has this
thing 54321 blast off it's silly but
it's like she's like been on podcast
talking about it and I started trying it
and it's very helpful you give yourself
five seconds Nico you want to snooze
all right you got five seconds this news
don't like you're not hitting the button
like could you lay there five
four three two one in on one no matter
what you make the deal with yourself
damn it that you get two feet on the
floor you get two feet on the floor
and you force yourself a smile and
you know whatever you got look you guys
know how it is within a minute of waking
up you already feel like so much better
if you're a depressed person you're
anxious person like within a minute of
waking up you all you want to do is go
back to bed you know you want to just it
feels so heavy you start just thinking
like God how am I gonna handle this [ __ ]
today and this [ __ ] and and like you
feel like a a one pound man who has to
every single day as a job lift up a
hundred pounds that's what depression
starts to feel like in the morning man
it really does and the anxiousness and
the anxiousness starts like I feel like
depression can really start to
start to add up all these depressed
thoughts and that gets our heart level
up and then we have you know things that
happen that are really kind of minor
inconveniences but they they set it off
you know like we saw Will Smith in this
lap he walked up and he slapped that
slap Chris Rock it wasn't just in the
moment it wasn't really even about like
the Jada thing it's like this dude had
some [ __ ] boiling up within his
relationship and we saw the release like
who are the people in your life that are
seeing the release and to be honest man
you need to take responsibility for the
actions that led up to that release
because if you woke up and you started
scrolling on social media boom you just
lost a point that's on you
you have to take action man you have to
get up out of bed both feet on the floor
and if your brain says like oh I feel
shitty I feel bad man it does all this
[ __ ] that our brain does and it's
[ __ ] mean and it's like it's whiny
and it's complaining
you got to talk back to it nap
I'm gonna make today the best day that I
can cool start thinking about things
you're grateful for literally like shut
up those thoughts by shoving in good
thoughts and again I mean maybe this
wording isn't the greatest because I
really don't want to do this spiritual
bypassing I really don't want to do the
shoving down of these things because you
got to bring them back up but I'm
telling you if you're unable to like
interact with your life if you're unable
to interact with these things that are
causing you suffering you've got to get
out of the fight or flight you've got to
get yourself to a place of listening to
yourself you've got to get yourself to a
place of like easing the pain easing the
um
easing the like
just
the storm man just the hail beating on
your window you know and and listen
brother I've been there and I know it so
well like and like dude you can be there
for years it feels like and and just
it's real
but
you have to do something about it I know
that sounds overly like dude I know that
sounds like insensitive that sounds like
dude what are you talking about you
really think I'm not doing anything
about it you really don't think I'm not
trying things there's so much more that
you could do and there's so much more
that you need to be doing
um on a physical level of like
actionable things that are going to add
up you know in a lot of those actionable
things are feeding your internal brain
your internal self with knowledge and
actionable I mean
when someone sends you a YouTube video
or or your wife says hey we should check
out this documentary it's about mental
health and like I'm just trying to like
help you out with your mental health and
you make some excuse that like to not
watch it
you're being a [ __ ]
that's what you're being you're being a
[ __ ] right now you need to take
responsibility for your own Mental
Health
and
man I I hope you feel the love when I
when I say it like I'm I'm hugging you
man I hope that doesn't sound
insensitive I hope I hope that doesn't
make you feel alone because that's not
my intention man I'm just saying like I
know it seems impossible I know it seems
like
like dude you think if I
like you think I'm not trying you know
you really think I'm not trying
I know you're trying
and
I'm just saying the things you're trying
if they're not working out for you you
need to try something else
there's so much wisdom out here there's
so much knowledge that you need to start
consuming think about what you watch all
day think about what you listen to all
day if you get in the car and you drive
to work and you just listen to the radio
or you just put on you know uh Spotify
hits or or the same playlist you've been
listening to that's like kind of sad
[ __ ] or it's like hardcore
um
I mean maybe it puts you in like a place
where you kind of feel good in that
moment
but if it's not putting you in place for
your whole day to succeed then you need
to change your habits you need to start
inserting like
like we've seen the movies you know they
make fun of them right in the movies
they have like this like chubby bald
dude who's like 40 something and he's
going through a midlife crisis and he
has a piece of [ __ ] car and he's driving
down the road and he's listening to like
the
um
listen to your thoughts
you are not your thoughts you are worthy
like you know like we see we've seen
that in movies and it almost seems like
something you need to make fun of but
I'm telling you if you're suffering
that's what you need to do you need to
find some mantras you need to find some
meditation you need to find some
positive thoughts because if you don't
have the ability to put in some positive
thoughts you need to consume some things
that will you need to step out of
yourself you need you step outside of
yourself and you stop the [ __ ] you
need to stop thinking that you have all
the answers because clearly you don't
have all the answers and
it's a very cold coffee at this point
and I don't have all the answers either
you know
I don't have the answers at all
I mean
like the answers to life what what's the
meaning of life how can I solve all your
problems with a podcast you know it's
not possible
but
my
my thing that I can do for me personally
is like this podcast and like stuff that
I create like if you know me at all you
know that I'm like a creative person I
love writing I love um look like I've
been around the last couple years I'm
writing like a ton of rap a lot of
hip-hop and I never I don't want to be a
rapper I'm not trying to be like a
Hip-Hop star I'm not trying to like get
famous or anything like that I'm
like it brings me joy it brings me joy
to work on these things and like I like
hanging out with myself when I'm writing
raps and I'm I'm pacing around the room
and I'm listening to beats and I'm like
looping the same thing and I'm just like
oh man that'd be so cool oh man oh that
rhymes and like it's just so it's this
fun exciting thing you know
you've got to you've got to find a way
for for you to enjoy learning and enjoy
that thing that you do like my my thing
when I'm doing all these things when I'm
recording this podcast that's my work
that's my like you have to find your
work the thing that only you can do
specifically you can do that you can
bring to this world
and it's and it's not a book it doesn't
have to be a book doesn't have to be a
podcast it doesn't have a YouTube
channel doesn't have to be a rap doesn't
have to be a song it doesn't have to be
um you know paper mache and you make
your your wife of you know the flower
picture you know
find what you do well
and work on it because when you're not
channeling your energy into
a version of yourself that's greater
than you are today in this moment
it seems like that space gets filled
with
I mean I don't know if it's like junk so
to say and that causes us to feel
inadequate or if there's just like this
thing that Wells up in the human psyche
of
um like feeling bad about ourselves and
feeling unable to handle things you know
and you have to
yeah man you almost have to in order to
get out of your own way you have to
consume other
ways of seeing the world and you know I
think therapy does this very well for
people their counselors because
you know when we're in our own head we
think we're like solving all these
things and we have all these different
points and well I guess this way it's
like no you it's like it's all just in
here circling and sometimes unless you
get some external input or someone
else's view from it
you're just going to keep repeating the
same things and like think you have
think you're solving answers you think
that you're coming up with conclusions
that make sense but they don't make
sense they just reaffirm your ego right
now like it reaffirms the safeness of
your ego the ego is the thing that is in
the cave and it's safe and it's like
it's this societal structure thing of
don't take action out there because
you're safe in here and like
man the the ego just want like if you
get the healthy stream of you know Dr
Pepper and Hot Pockets in your body
every day and you feel satiated so you
don't have the feelings of of hunger you
know like uh you know you don't feel the
suffering of hunger you know rather than
listening to hunger like what is hunger
is that actually a craving
oh it's a craving okay you can like
listen to it and introspect and
understand it
um when you are listening to just the
ego he wants you to stay in the cave man
he doesn't want you to
find out about life he doesn't want you
to you know you're Adam in the cave he
doesn't want you to go look for Eve you
know he doesn't want you to experience
life he doesn't want you to to wonder
what happens when you when you strike
that thing against that thing or wonder
what happens when you rub these two
sticks together and you make fire like
what is that you know it wants you to
stay safe in your cave and what's
happening is you're staying in your cave
and
you know maybe you are in a spot where
maybe you're in a spot where you're kind
of like coming out of the cave or you're
admitting I think again like I've said
if you're listening to this video or
someone sends it to you or you're in a
spot where like you're able to even
listen to a dude talk about depression
and anxiety and if you're still here
like 90 minutes in or whatever it is
that's crazy like awesome please give
yourself a pat on the bat because on the
back because you are making huge
progress because I the biggest step for
people with depression anxiety is this
denial stage of I don't have it I'm not
willing to face it
um I should feel shameful I'm just a bad
person I was born this way I'm stuck
like this I'm not going I'm not I'm not
going through this thing I'm stuck in it
it's who I am this is who I am for the
rest of my life I don't really see a
future out of it you know you're going
to be in these different stages if
you're in a stage where you're listening
to my me right now I just really
seriously sincerely stop and just say
man I'm on the right path because you're
on the right path and I'm not saying on
the right path because you're like
listening to me and I have all the all
the answers or anything I'm just saying
if you are listening to anybody at all
give you advice about your internal like
mental experience
and you have been suffering previous
prior to this then you are on the right
path you're helping it you know you're
it's like I said the first step of
um of you know the 12-step program is
admitting you have a problem like thing
is you have a problem you don't sit and
you wallow about it because what happens
with depression is we admit we have a
problem sometimes and then we go and I'm
just inadequate and nobody loves me and
they shouldn't love me because I'm a
total piece of [ __ ] and I should feel an
adequate and I am adequate and I can
never amount to anything and I'll never
be anything and I can't get out of this
and this is who I am and I might as well
have another hot pocket and I might as
well start another video game and I
might as well you know whatever the
thing is
you're not that you're not that you have
a problem you got to solve it that's
what being a human is you're a problem
solver it's seriously what this
experience is on Earth is like
like in a video game
I saw this thing uh in a video game you
know you know you're on the right path
in a video game because when you come
across the boss
but like that's how you know you're on
the right path like clearly you're not
going the wrong way like you know you
gotta level up right what happens in a
video game you get strong you start a
level one and you increase your mana and
you increase your health status and you
get items and they help you out and you
get spells um and you get cool clothes
too that's always cool
um you know and you learn and but but
listen if you tried to go against the
level 70 Boss when you're at level one
you're not it's not even gonna make any
[ __ ] sense you're not even gonna get
like one hit on him he's gonna hit you
once and you're gonna die life is like
this bro
your job is to recognize that you're on
level negative one right now and that
boss that boss bro you might think it's
like this big old hard thing because you
see these people like David Goggins and
they're running 58 miles and they're
they've got all these things like maybe
your boss is so level one that it's like
you gotta eat a banana today bro
yesterday you had Doritos for breakfast
today you have to throw the Doritos into
the trash and you got to eat a banana
today that's your boss
right and you know it like I said you
know it you can't deny these things in
your own mind you can't yeah you can't
[ __ ] yourself you have this internal
thing you have this little intuition we
call it you know you have this like
voice that knows exactly what you're
going to do that voice that remembers
okay I ate Doritos yesterday and I did
enjoy them they tasted really good
Doritos are really good
but I felt really crappy afterwards and
you know what I felt so crappy that an
hour later I kind of started to feel a
little sad and then an hour after that
I canceled my plans to go to coffee with
my friend because I was really feeling
sad and my my stomach kind of hurt and
whatever but if you can make the
correlation of like man I wonder if like
if I didn't eat Doritos for breakfast if
I would feel a little bit better
and then you do it and you eat a banana
for breakfast or you fast for breakfast
you have coffee without the creamer you
know you do these little things and you
start to you're like teaching your
background tasks you're teaching your
mind you know you're leveling up you're
increasing your Mana you're gaining a
couple items and then in a couple you
know a couple weeks a couple months you
might notice that like you you don't buy
Doritos anymore when you go to the store
you know what I mean because you're
being honest with yourself you're
um this is kind of an act of self-love
is not betraying yourself when you know
that you feel bad doing these things
like drinking is a big one man that's
that's a tough one I love you know
I think some of the connections that I
have in my life some of the friendships
that I have some of the men and women
that I've been able to have like such
deep profound beautiful connections and
conversations with I've had through
alcohol to be honest I'm this social
lubricant like I I've really always been
a fan of a couple you know a beer or two
um it just gets you like loose and it
makes me in that environment it's like a
lot going on and it really kind of helps
me like just be right here and not think
about all these tasks you know but
if the juice isn't worth the squeeze
like yeah you have good conversations
but that hangover is taking like two
days away from you or The Hangover is um
maybe you don't feel a hangover of the
sense of like
extreme sadness or extreme um
like physical pain like throwing up like
your typical hangover you know we hear
everybody's had a hangover right but
I think the day after drinking the day
after like indulging over indulging in
certain things
our mindset that day like we don't even
have the ability to show up for
ourselves or be strong for ourselves or
be patient with ourselves or have a good
conversation with ourselves or be nice
to ourselves or think about our future
goals or
um uh you know
like you got to look at where that puts
your mind these things that you're doing
that when you're doing them there's like
this hint of
uh I don't know if this is the best
thing for me and I'm not saying Society
since I'm not saying like
um God says that we shouldn't you know
God punishes the gays so you can't be
gay you know it's not like that I'm not
I'm just saying like there's not these
external rules out here brother there's
not these things that stop you out here
haven't you noticed it's all inside like
the suffering like these things that
people talk about in the in in Bible and
religious texts and like spiritual stuff
it's literally talking about the
internal systems of our mind because our
Eternal our internal systems create our
reality like it creates this like this
cup
this cup we call it a cut because it has
a purpose it fills my liquid in like if
I had never seen this before if I had no
use for this I wouldn't know I wouldn't
call this a cup I wouldn't know what it
is we see things as their usefulness our
structure of our reality is created by
in here it's it's
you need to update your firmware
our Hardware
is malfunctioning if you have depression
and anxiety and look at man the numbers
like again the numbers are crazy right
now it's like half of our half of
America is depressed like people are so
depressed and we don't know how to talk
about it we
it's like this impossible task and our
answer is go to the doctor and they'll
give you antidepressants and that's our
[ __ ] answer to this it's crazy
we
hmm
let me
to digress a bit
I want to end this soon I want to like
try to draw a conclusion
so I think our daily habits are huge
that's definitely something I want to
emphasize on here daily habits
the food you eat when you eat food
this might be a huge game changer for
people stop eating after like six or
seven p.m like literally anything like
if you you know have like a CBD treat or
like a weed treat before bed no that's
calories
if you wake up in the morning and you
have creamer in your coffee no like do
black coffee no calories
before you go to bed
make sure your stomach's not adjusting
when you wake up give yourself a few
hours before you before you digest maybe
try a smooth doesn't work for you
fasting really like started to help me
and help my mental cognition and I
switched to just black coffee too and my
coffee is just so great
um
you have to
you have to look at your daily habits
um
I know this shit's obvious and I know
it's it's like well dude I do my daily
habits so I can like feel okay because I
just feel shitty all day so of course I
want like a video game to at least feel
a little bit of happiness it's like the
one time I hang out with my friends is
on a video game or it's like the one
time that I get to have a good day is
when I'm drinking a beer at the end of
the day or like
um you know I I I work hard all day so I
can have a giant
you know I don't get off work till 10 pm
and so I have to have like a giant meal
at 11 p.m and it's just like it's not I
can't help it well
look man these things are affecting you
so it's up to you and nobody else to
figure out what's next like if if
something you are doing or something in
your life is affecting you you cannot
sit on the ground and go I don't know
what to do about it I can't do anything
I guess I'll just suffer it's up to you
there is nobody coming to save you
there's nobody coming to pick you up off
the ground in these situations if you
are suffering and there's answers
dangling right in front of you and
you're ignoring them
this is The Telltale thing of you can't
help someone who does not help
themselves
as someone who is is man I'm really
trying to help people
maybe I'm doing it in my own terms maybe
I'm maybe I'm like way too sloppy about
this maybe I should keep my mouth shut
but like
like what what when are you gonna
[ __ ] listen who are you gonna listen
to
I would hate to see my friends and loved
ones and people that I that I respect
and love and people who are just like me
people that I don't know young people do
not I mean I'm 30 I think about like all
these kids who are are
teenagers and 20 who are killing
themselves who are who are
like they clearly don't have the right
answers clearly we're not speaking to
them properly clearly nobody is saying
the right things
like like
what what the [ __ ] is going on here
clearly the answer of go to the doctor
and get antidepressants
isn't working
you know
like at what point like like
when a medicine isn't working at what
point do you stop taking it
at what point do you get to the root of
the problem
and
you know
I I hope that people can find like
something to to take in this and I'm not
trying to be like grandiose I'm like I'm
I'm doing what I'm doing God's work here
I'm really helped I'm saving I'm saving
men's mental health in the modern era
I'm not trying to come from that space I
I'm trying to like I hope I can say
things I hope I'm saying things in ways
you haven't heard before
I think our I think our world is so
[ __ ] soft right now in a way that is
harming our men it's really harming our
men like we think we're supposed to be
soft back but like really we need to
like stand up and be sturdy and it's not
stand up and shove down those things
it's seriously like
I I am the problem something I'm doing
is not working out
and listen listen don't feel guilty
don't feel shameful about this
me saying I'm the problem for me
personally correlates to
I'm the problem because
I haven't taken the time to really sit
down and assess what happened to me as a
child
I'm the problem
because my cousin and very close friend
died
and it really traumatized me and I
really never healed from it in in
I only sleep very well unless I have a
couple drinks before
I'm the problem
because
I didn't take the time in the morning to
get my mind right and so I screamed at
my daughter
at 11 30 A.M
and I wish I didn't
I'm the problem
because I didn't take action because I'm
feeling the exact same feelings that
I've been feeling because I've been
suffering and I'm suffering the exact
same way I'm suffering today that I was
yesterday and I've done nothing
differently
and I'm pretending
that well I don't know
God I don't know I can't do it why am I
feeling like this
my stomach hurts
why did I eat Doritos it's not related
there is
I would hate because I know that the
depressed mind
you know I'm kind of like being
facetious and jokey right I want to
recognize that I know the depressant
anxious mind is so [ __ ] mean to us
that like
what you might be hearing right now is
I'm the problem
you're like you're telling yourself that
and that's not true
there is a problem though
that's huge
because
I think a lot of what we do is we deny
this [ __ ]
we deny it because it's like seriously
freaky to look at
like you almost convinced like you're
like dude I'm going crazy I'm nuts
they're gonna lock me up or something if
people knew what my inter if people only
knew what I was thinking about they
would think I'm a [ __ ] freak
does that sound familiar
I'm telling you bro
millions of people
men and women feel the same way but we
can't have a conversation about it we
have these weird dancing around
conversations and and we can't be adult
we can't be grown-ups about this [ __ ]
and just talk about it and just like
man the the big thing it's like it's not
you aren't the problem it's like but
there is a problem
there's a problem and when you when you
can say that there is a problem
you can then begin
to unwind it
it kind of loses its umph you know
there's this maybe I'll end with this
if you guys have ever heard the snake
the rope and the snake analogy you know
say you're on a on a walk and kind of
corner of your eye you see a snake you
know oh [ __ ] when you jump in your body
and like think about it like there's
this biochemical process
chemicals are released in your body it's
happened through Evolution like think
about it you literally die if you get
bit by a snake over the course of all
these years so of course it makes sense
to well don't want to give up on that
snake it frees us out it's not about our
personality going I just don't
personally like snakes it's really like
an evolutionary thing so my car our
primitive structure is activated by
seeing a snake
okay so you're walking you saw a snake
ah freaked out
you're tense your shoulders are tense
your muscles are tense
your anxiety is up cortisol is up
walk a little bit farther a couple more
feet
a little more light shines on that snake
oh
it was actually just a rope in the shape
of a snake in my mind saw a snake
oh so what do you do now do you walk
around in tent state or do you drop your
shoulders and go uh
[Music]
it was never a snake
my friend it was never a snake
you need to see
the what's going on with you
is a rope
and just to extend this analogy farther
this might be so corny but like
climb up that rope you know
like maybe that's a rope down into the
the well that you're in maybe that's a
rope down into the cave that you're in
and it's not a snake you don't have to
hide from it you know it's not a snake
dangling there it's it's like the thing
is if if you look at it you realize it's
not a snake damn it you gotta look at it
look at it
sit with it
and we hear that a lot sit with it what
does that mean it's like some like
hippie meditation thing sit with it
that means we start thinking about these
things
and you don't have a pro a solution you
don't have a way to solve it
you
you get new information
you absorb more information you write
out the things that are in your head
because what happens is we have these
things that start coming and they and
they they Loop and we're like I don't
know the answers to this this is tough
this hurts it feels anxious like in your
body we're so out of touch with our body
our bodies start to feel anxious and
intense up you know just just as if we
saw a snake and
in order for our bodies to like relax
instead of truly relaxing in a sense of
like ah it was never a snake
we go
we'll grab our phone so we grab a
Snickers bar we grab a beer we grab
whatever our thing is and we've all got
them and I've got plenty man don't let
me make you feel guilty about it I've
got my [ __ ] too I love my phone I'm
always on this damn thing
but instead of
looking for a few minutes just staring
at the shape of that snake and allowing
our minds to kind of go okay
now that I look at it it kind of looks
like it's like
Tan in like a rope is that a rope
what we do is we turn our backs to this
thing that hurts right we turn our backs
we look away and we look over here at
our phone we look over at our Snickers
we turn our TV on or we get our
distractions or we look up porn or we
um we try to find love from another
person we look at like girls photos and
we like them we think maybe they're
going to feel it make us feel fulfilled
and we're doing a bunch of stuff that
we're not really conscious that we're
doing it's like our ego is trying to
help us out but it's actually sabotaging
us more and we think that's okay we're
looking for like short-term pleasure to
cover over
um real and long-term
pain and anguish
you know we have these things that
really happen to us maybe that really
was a snake you know what I mean
but is it here anymore
you don't need to carry that snake in
your back pocket and always run from
your back pocket you know what I mean
there's ways to bring up these things
and step into who you really are
there's ways to
to not turn away from the Snake Man
and
again and again I have to emphasize like
do not allow yourself to feel guilty or
shameful about these things you're not
going to solve it that way man
maybe you have something you should be
ashamed about maybe you have something
you should actually feel guilty for
all right
you felt it I'm sure you felt it for
more than a day huh I'm sure you felt
that [ __ ] for weeks months years
I've done things that I've been shameful
about that I lit like I mean
man
I have
if you've ever been unfaithful in a
relationship
that will stick with you all day
they'll stay with you all day every day
at all times you're waiting for a text
to come in that's bad text you're
waiting for a you're waiting for your
whole illusion to just break down you
know and it's all this anxiety and it's
all this
distraction from what's really here
you're like living layers back because
you're protecting this thing that's
painful
and what you really got to do is is go
hang on a minute and you look over your
shoulder
and you stare at it and you wonder about
it go huh okay
yeah that hurts man it hurts right now
to look at it hurts to look at right
this second
I don't think I could solve it all right
now okay what can I solve
can I look at this can I at least ask
myself maybe I'm not going to get to the
bottom of it but
all right I was unfaithful why was I
unfaithful
it just doesn't seem like something I
would want to do
I hurt myself I hurt the other person
why would I want to do that
cool maybe that's step one maybe you
looked at like why you did this thing
maybe you looked at something you're
guilty about maybe looked at something
you're feeling shameful about maybe you
looked at your inadequacies maybe you
looked at um you know maybe you're
reliving the the with the winning play
that you missed in your senior year of
high school and you were the quarterback
and you [ __ ] you shanked it man
he shanked it your whole life could have
been different
you could have could have been D1 bruh
could've been playing in the NFL if that
would have went there's all this story
that's going to add up over time too and
you're just going to make yourself feel
guilty about that one instance of you
know kind of throwing the football off
you got to look at that [ __ ] and realize
that it's fueling you
it's it's
these background tasks are responsible
for your everyday reactions if you are
reacting from a place of anxiousness if
you're reacting from a place of high
anxiety
you might have background tasks that
you're still fighting you might still be
in fist fights from years ago
in the body keeps the score there's even
a book called the body keeps the score
you hold on to these things you saw that
snake oh you tensed up
and then you just walked around like
that for the rest of your life bro with
your shoulders all scrunched up and at
some point someone's like hey bro the
snake was never a snake it's just a rope
and you can't hear [ __ ] because you
ain't listening because you think you
know the answers because you aren't
[ __ ] listening
listen
and not just to me listen to yourself
please listen to yourself
don't believe everything you think but
listen
I think you're gonna know when you just
listen that
some things aren't true you know you're
gonna your mind is Gonna Fill In things
and tell you things that aren't true
and if it's not like from a place of
love if it's not a positive thought a
place of
how can I best show up for these people
that I love and love me and what a gift
it is to be in this position because you
know as it turns out love isn't free you
can't just walk up to anybody and say
hey you want to be best friends hey you
want to be my wife and be my close you
know my close partner hey you want to
raise a child together you are in a
specific peculiar beautiful special spot
where you're at look around man have a
little gratitude
do you have your parents in your life do
you have friends do you have a wife do
you have a loved one do you have
neighbors do you have a community do you
have people at work that you enjoy like
whatever you do have you have to be able
to pinpoint it and look at it and go
okay yeah
all right I got it I got and I also got
responsibilities to show up for those
people and it really is this beautiful
thing this active service you're gonna
read that and if you dive into any sort
of like religious
community-based uh uh I mean religious
this in the word um
there's these communities in service
it's another thing about the human
psyche is when you are in service to
others you're able to step out of your
own [ __ ] and you're not thinking
about all these things you know like
when you're serving someone else you're
not serving them so you can get
something
but hell if that's where you're starting
cool if you're like damn it I feel
terrible I'm gonna go to the soup
kitchen so maybe I'll at least feel
better about serving serving you know a
bum some slop or whatever you know maybe
that's an insensitive way of putting
that but um I like
in that moment
bro when you're looking at some dude
who's got a sleeping bag in a pair of
pants with only one leg still left on it
because he needed some shorts just on
that side the day before
and he's sleeping on the sidewalk in
downtown Austin you think you're [ __ ]
thinking about what you got going on no
and what happens in that moment when
we're able to serve someone else and
step outside of our crap is in the
background these background tests that I
was saying you got to look at and it
starts to like work itself out in a
weird way it's like this mystical
marvelous thing the universe does is
when you get out of your own way
your body kind of becomes quiet when you
serve other people when you help other
people your body becomes quiet and it's
like you don't have to intellectualize
all these things you don't have to like
I know I've been saying you know get
this knowledge and shove it down your
throat and read these books and listen
to these podcasts and
um you know watch his YouTube videos and
all this stuff there's that but there's
there's this silence that happens when
you're in service to others when you're
in a quiet place
if you're able to meditate this is what
happens as well is you're not you know
when you're meditating you're not
you're not solving all your problems you
dork you're solving any of your problems
you're stepping out of your way so when
you're breathing and you're
concentrating on your breath and
meditation you've all heard this like
all you got to do is follow your breath
what happens is the you the you yourself
that follows the breath you stop
thinking about yourself therefore you
stop existing in that moment and so all
of your old stories can kind of meh they
start to fall away and you kind of get
more in peace with what's actually here
and you stop interacting with all these
stories you stop overlaying your traumas
onto every interaction that you have you
stop putting the face of the people who
hurt you on the face of everyone you
interact with and suddenly you see who
they really are and they see who you
really are and your interactions
suddenly give you a permission to just
be to just be this person who's not
trying to not be depressed who's not
trying to not be anxious who's not
trying to uh you know push away the bad
thoughts that are happening as he's in
the middle of this conversation right
now
this takes work there's nothing that
I've said in this in this podcast
episode there's nothing that I'll send
anybody there's nothing that I will
suggest to anybody that's going to solve
all your problems there's nothing that
you can do that is going to in one
instant I mean you you don't this is
work
you gotta [ __ ] listen you gotta work
sorry
this is going to take
I mean I don't know I'm On A peculiar
path because I'm doing this super out
loud and I'm so obsessed with this stuff
and but it's it's been years you know
and I'm I'm I want to tell you I'm not
I'm not in like a place where I never
feel sadness
I feel sad I still get depressed days
um I still
um
and by depressed days even that like I
don't like saying that I still have days
where it seems that
where I have the human feeling of
depression
it's not all day
because look even if I want to say it's
all day I could listen to a funny
podcast and crack a joke suddenly I'm
laughing but then you remember like oh
yeah but I'm a depressed person oh yeah
all those sad things you know it's just
like an argument if you're having an
argument with someone in your head what
you're doing is you're continuously
bringing up that argument and you're not
allowing the anger the thing to
dissipate your job is to shut up
to shut up and listen
you know you gotta just
allow
the better version of you
to come forth and you have to take
action as well as shut up and listen
and you'll know when it's time to do
either of those things or any of those
things I mean
you
who you are now
will be unrecognizable
no sorry
who you are now
will be held with understanding and love
in the future
you need to be able to go to a growth
mindset you need to be able to
say look
I don't say this a ton of times already
but look what I've been doing is not
working out for me what's been happening
is not working out for me it's not my
brain is attacking me and I'm suffering
no that's not it
that puts you in a place of no action it
puts you in a place of not being able to
do anything man
it's life in your reaction to it and I
get that
it's gonna feel super fake and trust me
it will feel super fake very often but
the repetition of when your mind feels
shitty and it's feeding you these bad
thoughts and you wake up in the morning
and it's like [ __ ] you dude you suck
you're a big dummy
your job even if it doesn't feel genuine
your job your work
as a man as a provider to people around
you your job
work you have to do this or you will die
damn it
you have to say no
no brain
nah man separate yourself into a
depressed version of yourself and into a
loving version of yourself
the real you and the depressed you and
when you depressed version of you is
saying man I'm doing this and I hated I
did this and I'm regretful of this and
I'm not worthy of this and I'm so sad
you say nah
all right what can I do you know what
makes me happy at least 1.2 percent
happier than I'm feeling right now is a
walk outside with some vitamin D on my
skin with some sun shining directly on
my skin
go for a walk do something tell your
mind no
and it's not shoving it down it's
getting to a point where you can then
sit with it later on you don't just wait
till it's an emergency to to handle this
stuff breath work and all these sorts of
things these aren't for just when you're
having anxiety or a panic attack breath
work is you're breathing at all times
right now you're [ __ ] breathing are
you breathing from your diaphragm or up
in your chest are you breathing really
shallow are you breathing through your
mouth what you need to be doing is
breathing through your nose pretty much
at all times breathing Slow and Low deep
breaths and you can train yourself to
breathe more smoothly and slowly and it
actually raises your overall levels of
anxiousness on a constant basis down
trust me trust me trust me think about
it biologically when we see a snake we
see a lion there's a lion over there
heart rate cool get prepared send blood
to all of the limbs we got a Sprint bro
we got a gtf out of here we gotta go
you're you stop digesting properly your
fingernails aren't it's not time to grow
oh are you kidding me if you gotta run
from a [ __ ] lion you think it's time
for your body to go like hey let's make
sure that we have the right amount of of
blood flow and and proper things going
to The Nail so we can make sure they
grow strong and sturdy it's like no no
what's not used right now to make this
body survive this potential lion or
snake attack
shut it down
and you're in a state of that
you have things that are happening in
your body that are shut down because
you're in a state of fight or flight and
you're not thinking logically because of
it you're sick because of it I'm telling
you like I'm looking you in the eye man
through the camera if you're watching
this on YouTube I'm I'm telling you
you're not thinking clearly you have to
get to a place where
you're calm and that doesn't mean you
could solve all your problems and you
you know forgive everybody whoever hurts
you in your childhood and all these
things it's no no right here right now
where you're at share all those things
cool yep but right here can you be where
you're at
for a few minutes 10 minutes five
minutes two minutes and you and you
focus on your breath
you focus on your breath
you know you're training this thing
you're training your breath right
when you have an anxiety attack if you
felt those panic attack your heart
rate's up you feel like it's gonna
[ __ ] explode you pretty sure you're
gonna have a heart attack it's like a
thing like multiple people tons of
people by the way if you've ever gone to
the hospital for a panic attack or you
wanted to or anxiety attack tons of
dudes go to the hospital for panic
attack tons of people and they when they
tell me about this and I hear about it
through through other podcasts and
YouTube videos and stuff too but when
people tell me about this they're still
in denial that like they're still in a
place of I'm pretty sure it's not just
anxiety man like there's no way anxiety
is like that I literally thought I was
gonna die yeah anxiety can get that bad
your internal thoughts can make your
body think that there's a line about to
murder you and you get stuck in that for
hours on end and think about all the
processes in your body that are no
longer working properly your digesting
your fingernails your um your mental
cognacies your your memory
um your your ability to be patient and
present with with children or your loved
ones or your dog or you know any of
these things the
the
you have to get quiet Okay so
let's wrap this up when you get in the
morning wake up in the morning and
you're feeling bad you say no
it's not an option all right it doesn't
have to be
unless that's really what you need if
you if what you need sometimes what I
needed was I needed to run 14 miles and
be so exhausted that my brain couldn't
fight me anymore so then I could finally
sit in meditation if that's what it's
going to take you then you need to
[ __ ] do it it's your job to do it
damn it do it you can do it you can
handle it you're worthy of it who you
are right now the person you're telling
yourself that you're that you've been
been or that you've been um I'm showing
up as this person who is like inadequate
this person who you're like he's he's
depressed and um he's just an anxious
person like this view of yourself that
you've painted
[ __ ] that guy
that ain't you man
you're strong you're brave each one of
us as men as as women as all of us we
have the ability to be brave and
courageous and strong and willing and
and wise and knowledgeable but we have
to take action we have to take action
and we have to listen
so
please I mean all this stuff
all this stuff I know it's such a
doorway
but just open it that's all you got to
do I think is if you've listened to this
I hope that I've already supplied you
with at least a few things that make
sense but man from here go to YouTube
and search Ted Talk depression Ted Talk
anxiety TED Talk
men's mental health like start there and
okay so that speaker oh they have a
podcast well listen to that what do they
have to say oh that speaker who wrote
that man he said some really good points
about anxiety I never even thought about
anxiety like that oh he's been a podcast
guest on oh he's been on Joe Rogan well
I know Joe a lot of people like Joe
Rogan I'll I'll watch that one cool I
just listened to three hour podcast and
in that podcast he mentioned this book
that his therapist suggested to him cool
I'll give that I'll give that book a try
your path your way out this rope that's
being thrown down to you is this way
this is how you do it this is look man I
think I I mean a lot of my a lot of my
age group on here is is Millennials and
stuff I don't have a ton of young people
on here
um but I think that
what I try to do a lot of the times is I
try to strengthen it and empower the
people my age as much as I can or maybe
a little bit younger because I truly
think that these younger Generations are
going to need
um
um Divine teachings like they're going
to need us they're going to need us to
act and speak logically and truthfully
and um
from a place of authenticity in our
being you know because they're going to
be suffering like man the technology and
the social media and just the the
changing and the food and all of this
man uh
think about it where you're at right now
you think you're going to be there
forever that's [ __ ] it's not true
it's no longer true be willing I'm
telling you right now
tell yourself nah it ain't gonna happen
if for whatever crazy reason you're
still two hours in listening to this
right now you're done
you're on the you're on the uphill
brother it's time
you're working on it and that doesn't
mean it's going to go away and that
doesn't mean that you don't feel
depression or anxiety anymore you might
feel it tomorrow you might feel later
tonight but you're not going to sit and
take it you're not going to lay down in
the storm you're not going to just oh
get your ass kicked every day you're
going to start fighting back
and when you fight back you're able to
be quiet with yourself you're able to
listen be able to hear what's actually
being said and you're able to get
yourself out of the way so you can try
it out so you can try to believe it what
would it be like to believe that
what would it be like to
I wonder what when that lady talks about
her anxiety that doesn't sound at all
like my anxiety but I wonder what it
would feel like to be in her shoes huh
and you shut yourself up you stop trying
to put yourself into that situation you
just listen to what this lady is saying
about anxiety or whatever and
her conclusions her way out start to
give you a little bit of a portal you
know like you start to go ah
okay I have a similar thing that like I
can yeah I guess I could probably try
that or like oh you don't like running
but you you know you can do a yoga video
on YouTube from your TV all right that's
something start your day with that
listen man you got to work with from
where you're at um I feel like I can
keep rambling about this forever so
listen please anybody message me on
Instagram Jacob from the internet if
you're um if there's anything that I can
provide you if there's any books that I
can suggest if there's any YouTube
videos or podcasts um uh anything I
could do to
I hope that it's
sincerely I'm trying to help because I
see suffering and I'm in
brother you don't have to suffer so much
you know
you need more information
and you need action
so please reach out Jacob from the
internet on Instagram I have been on
Facebook more lately but you know I
don't know how long that's gonna last
that place is a cesspool of butts
um I hope this helps if you guys have
any interaction or
um if you disagree with everything I
said please I would love to speak more
eloquently not carefully I do not like I
don't think we should police ourselves
with this mental health stuff I think we
treat everybody like they're fragile
sissies and I think that that's that
backwards law is they feel like they're
fragile sissies because we're treating
them like okay honey and there's there's
softness that needs to happen and that
is very important and I think you know
therapists and counselors are for that
but [ __ ] man my role I'm
I'm I used to manage skate shops I've
been a DJ for 10 years I have a podcast
I have two full sleeves like I'm not I'm
not I'm just trying to be who I am and
try to show up for you as as as what I
can really offer and and um you know
I I hope that I haven't said anything
that harms anyone I know that this is
very very
um
this is a weird it's a it's a touchy
subject because I mean I think with
depression there's there's this risk of
suicide and
I think everyone is so careful to say
the right or wrong things around someone
who's suicidal and it makes them feel
more ostracized bro and like I just want
to be the person to say I've been
suicidal as [ __ ] man I've held a I've
held a loaded gun up to my temple
um
and
I just
I'm so different now man I really I have
learned so much like the work reality is
so different now
and I just want
I want people who are in that spot for
whatever reason if you're in that spot
you just
there's a malfunction brother it's not
who you are
it's just there's something not working
properly it's not you
it's not you bud
you're fine maybe you haven't been like
taking the right actions or maybe you
like you know maybe made some mistakes
maybe you [ __ ] up maybe you said the
wrong things maybe there's a lot of work
on your personality that needs done
maybe you're not even like that likable
of maybe you're kind of a [ __ ] to be
around whatever cool it's where you're
at brother it's not it's not worth
making yourself feel guilty but if you
want a different life outside of this if
you want to stop suffering you're going
to have to be a different person you're
gonna have to change your identity
change who you are and that starts with
admitting cool this ain't working out
for me and that's where you're at right
now if you're listening to this episode
I hope that's exactly where you're at if
you have already admitted that and
somehow this has helped you if you have
anybody you can send this to that you
think might help them
uh if you have a clip out of this you
can take like if there's maybe even just
one sense or a minute long like whatever
whatever you can do
I hope this helps anyway
you know the deal love yourself drink
plenty of water
um
it was never a snake brother
I love you I'll see you guys next
episode
thanks for listening